Guide to the Edmund M. Cameron Records, 1929 - 1972 UA.29.02.0029
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Edmund M. Cameron records
1929 - 1972
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Cameron, Edmund McCullough, 1902-1988
UA.29.02.0029
13.5 Linear Feet
Edmund "Eddie" McCullough Cameron (1902-1988) served as head basketball coach, head football coach, and Athletic Director during his 46 year career at Duke University. He was known for enhancing Duke athletics and the Department of Physical Education by improving and adding facilities and expanding athletic programs. The Cameron Indoor Stadium at Duke was named in his honor. The Cameron papers include correspondence, reports, memoranda, scrapbooks, and other printed materials. Among the major subjects of the collection are the Duke basketball and football teams, the Duke athletic department, the Duke Department of Physical Education, collegiate athletics, the National Collegiate Athletic Association, and the Atlantic Coast Conference. English.
Access Restrictions
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
For a period of twenty-five years from the origin of the material, permission in writing from the office of origin and the University Archivist is required for use. After twenty-five years, records that have been processed may be consulted with the permission of the University Archivist.
Records, such as search committee files or others pertaining to employment where individuals are identified, are closed for 70 years.
In accordance with the Family Education Rights and Privacy Act of 1974 as amended, Duke University permits students to inspect their education records and limits the disclosure of personally identifiable information from education records.
Unprocessed materials are closed pending processing.
Provenance
The Edmund M. Cameron Records were received by the University Archives as a gift in 1972 (A72-30), 1973 (A73-74, A73-122), 1989 (A89-0052), and 1990 (A90-99).
Biographical Note
Edmund "Eddie" McCullough Cameron was born on April 22, 1902, in Manor, Pennsylvania. An excellent student, Cameron also won acclaim for his athletic talents at the Culver Military Academy and Washington and Lee University. He joined Duke University in 1926 as the freshmen football, basketball, and baseball coach. In 1929, Cameron was named head basketball coach. He also assisted in coaching football with head coach Wallace Wade. In 1942, Cameron became head football coach, and in 1946 he again served as assistant coach with Wade. Both the basketball and football teams experienced record successes under Cameron's leadership.
In 1951, Cameron was named Athletic Director, and also directed the Department of Physical Education. He expanded the range and quality of athletic facilities at Duke. In 1953, he helped found the Atlantic Coast Conference and served as chairman of the ACC Basketball Committee for 19 years. He also chaired the basketball committee in the Southern Conference for 20 years.
Cameron was inducted into the North Carolina Sports Hall of Fame in 1969. In 1972, the Duke Indoor Stadium was renamed the Cameron Indoor Stadium. Cameron retired on August 31 of that same year. He died on November 25, 1988, at the age of 86. He was survived by his wife of over 50 years, Mary Toms Cameron, and four children.
Collection Overview
The collection includes correspondence, reports, memoranda, scrapbooks, and other materials related to Cameron's career at Duke University. The first series, Subject Files, consists of office files, primarily correspondence, from the 1950s to the early 1970s, during Cameron's term as Athletic Director. The second series, Correspondence, also consists of some professional correspondence, but includes a number of personal letters and dates from the 1940s to the 1970s. The Clippings series is a brief collection of articles saved by Cameron. The Manuals and Printed Materials series includes reports and guides published by the NCAA and the ACC during the 1950s through the 1970s. The Scrapbooks series consists of three disassembled scrapbooks dating from the 1920s through the 1970s. These books include correspondence, photographs, newspaper and magazine clippings, game programs, and tickets and other memorabilia.
Related Material
Department of Athletics Records
Duke University Archives
Office of Sports Information and Promotion Records
Duke University Archives
College sports; National Collegiate Athletic Association; Duke University -- Football; Duke University -- Basketball; Duke University. Dept. of Athletics; Duke University. Cameron Indoor Stadium; Atlantic Coast Conference; Duke University -- Athletics; Cameron, Edmund McCullough, 1902-1988
- Subject Files
  Scope and Contents note
  These materials came from accession numbers A72-30, A73-74, and A73-122, and were the office files of Cameron. Minutes of the Academic Council were removed to the Academic Council collection. Discarded materials include: routine applications for administrative assistant positions; most applications for Sports Information Director's position (representative sample retained); detailed monthly financial statements, receipts, IRI forms, and travel vouchers; most financial statements prepared by Peat, Marwick and Mitchell for individual football games (representative sample retained); most football game trip itineraries (representative sample retained); and golf course auxiliary expense forms.
  - Admissions Policy (Box 1)
  - Applications [for staff positions] - RESTRICTED [Personnel Information]
    - Baseball (Box 1)
    - Basketball, [2 folders] (Box 1)
    - Football, [4 folders] (Box 1)
    - Gymnastics (Box 1)
    - Lacrosse (Box 1)
    - General, P.E., [2 folders] (Box 1)
    - Soccer (Box 1)
    - Sports Publicity (Box 1)
    - Swimming (Box 1)
    - Tennis (Box 1)
    - Track and Cross Country (Box 1)
    - Wrestling (Box 1)
  - Athletic Council
    - 1967-1968 (Box 1)
    - 1968-1969 (Box 1)
    - 1969-1970 (Box 1)
    - Financial Reports, 1964-1968 (Box 1)
  - Athletic Equipment Room Inventory, 1965-1966 (Box 1)
  - Athletic Facilities
    - Aquatic Center, [2 folders] (Box 1)
    - Card Gymnasium (Box 1)
    - Construction, Policy (Box 1)
    - Golf, Women's Driving Range on East (Box 1)
    - Golf Course
      - Construction (Box 1)
      - Shop and Storage Construction (Box 1)
      - Corrections and Improvements (Box 1)
      - Highway Problems (Box 1)
      - Grounds Keeper's House (Box 1)
      - Maintenance (Box 1)
    - Indoor Stadium
      - Locker Room Renovation, 1967-1968 (Box 1)
      - Football Offices (Box 1)
      - Flooring (Box 1)
      - Improvements (Box 1)
      - Space Allocations (Box 1)
      - Reservations (Box 1)
    - Intramural Building (Box 1)
    - Laundry (Box 1)
    - "Limited Life" Building (football) (Box 1)
    - Maintenance and Improvements (Box 1)
    - Overcrowding of Facilities for P.E. (Box 1)
    - General Committee on West Campus Athletic Educational Facilities (Box 1)
    - Scheduling (Box 1)
    - Squash Courts (Box 1)
    - Tennis Courts (Box 1)
    - Track (Box 1)
    - Wallace Wade Stadium
      - Expansion and Fundraising (Box 1)
      - Painting (Box 1)
      - Management (Box 1)
      - Lighting, 1966-1967 (Box 1)
  - Athletic Fund (Box 1)
  - Athletic Program (Box 1)
  - Athletic Program, Faculty Committee Report, 1969-1970 (Box 1)
  - Athletics and Academics (Box 1)
  - Athletics and P.E. Organization (Box 1)
  - Atlantic Coast Conference (Box 2)
    - Annual Report, 1969 (Box 2)
    - Beauty Contest (Box 2)
    - Basketball Committee, 1959-1972, [5 folders] (Box 2)
    - Basketball Tournament (Box 2)
    - General, 1961-1972, [5 folders] (Box 2)
    - General Representative Audits (Box 2)
    - Basketball - Television Report (Box 2)
  - Baseball (Box 2)
  - Baseball, Summer League, 1968 (Box 2)
  - Basketball
    - Clinic for Boys (Box 2)
    - Big Four Freshman Tournament (Box 2)
    - Crowd Behavior (Box 2)
    - Financial Report, 1951-1970 (Box 2)
    - Hall of Fame (Box 2)
    - National Invitation Tournament (Box 2)
    - Newspaper Coverage, Duke vs. UNC, 1966-1967 (Box 2)
    - N.C. High School Association (Box 2)
    - Southern Conference, 1947 (Box 2)
    - Southern Conference, Tournament Program, 1934 (Box 2)
    - U.S.C./McGuire Controversy (Box 2)
  - Big Four Athletic Directors, 1968-1971 (Box 2)
  - Black Athletes (Box 2)
  - Blue Devils Club (Box 2)
  - Blue Trident (Box 2)
  - Brusie, Dick (SID) (Box 2)
  - Bubas, Vic (Box 2)
  - Budget (Box 2)
  - Budget, Minor Sports (Box 2)
  - Carmichael Cup (Box 2)
  - Carpenter, R.M.M. (Box 2)
  - Cheating Scandal (Box 2)
  - Coaching Problems - Basketball and Football (Box 2)
  - Correspondence, 1952-1971 and no date, [3 folders] (Box 2)
  - Cross Country (Box 2)
  - Development, Fifth Decade (Box 2)
  - Development Office, 1970-1971 (Box 2)
  - Dixie Classic, 1966-1967 (Box 2)
  - Durham High School Track Day, 1967 (Box 2)
  - Durham Sports Club (Box 2)
  - Fencing, 1962-1972 (Box 3)
  - Film Library (Box 3)
  - Football
    - Academic Performance Forecast (Box 3)
    - ACC Contracts (Box 3)
    - Games, State-Duke, 1967 (Box 3)
    - Game Financial Statements (Box 3)
    - Game trips (Box 3)
    - Gator Bowl (University of Florida), 1970 (Box 3)
    - Injury Reports (Box 3)
    - Oyster Bowl, 1967-1969 (Box 3)
    - Photographer's Agreement, 1966 (Box 3)
    - Players - RESTRICTED [Student Information]
      - Sam Barton (Box 3)
      - Bruce Campbell (Box 3)
      - Charles Guy (Box 3)
      - Robert Henry (Box 3)
      - Patrick Martin (Box 3)
      - Bruce Reynolds (Box 3)
      - Peter Schafer (Box 3)
      - Al Woodall (Box 3)
      - Profiles (Box 3)
      - Releases (Box 3)
      - Signees, 1971 (Box 3)
    - Policy, 1961-1965 (Box 3)
    - Recruiting Problems, National, 1967 (Box 3)
    - Rose Bowl
      - Contract, 1941 (Box 3)
      - Team List, 1941 (Box 3)
      - 1941-1942, [3 folders] (Box 3)
    - Schedule (Box 3)
    - Staff Changes, 1966 (Box 3)
    - Sugar Bowl, 1945 (Box 3)
  - Fundraising (Box 3)
  - Fundraising
    - Bly-Persons Field House, 1968-1969 (Box 3)
    - Swimming Pool Contributors, 1969-1971 (Box 3)
  - Golf (Box 3)
  - Golf Course, Use of Course (Box 3)
  - Golf Course Committee, 1967-1971, [2 folders] (Box 3)
  - Golf Course Scheduling - Tournaments (Box 3)
  - Golf Shop Sales (Box 3)
  - Graduate Student Protests (Box 3)
  - Hall of Fame Recommendations (Box 3)
  - Huestis, Charles (Box 3)
  - Intercollegiate Association of Amateur Athletes of America (IC4A) (Box 3)
  - Internal Development and Alumni Relations Council (Box 3)
  - Intramural Board Minutes, 1964-1971 (Box 3)
  - Intramural Program - Correspondence, Flyers (Box 3)
  - Knight, Douglas M. (Box 3)
  - Lacrosse, 1966-1968 (Box 3)
  - Liability for Transporting Athletes (Box 3)
  - Long Range Planning Committee, Subcommittee for Facilities (Box 3)
  - Managerial Program, 1966-1967 (Box 3)
  - Mann, Glenn E ("Ted"), 1966-1967 (Box 3)
  - Marching Band, Videotape (Box 3)
  - McGee, Mike (Box 3)
  - Morehead Scholarship Information, 1962-1967 (Box 3)
  - NCAA
    - Cost of Intercollegiate Athletic Programs (Box 3)
    - 1.600 Rule (Box 3)
    - Delegate (Box 3)
    - 1957-1963 (Box 3)
    - 1963-1965 (Box 3)
    - 1965-1967 (Box 3)
    - 1967-1970 (Box 3)
    - Printed Material, 1970-1971 (Box 3)
  - National Association of Athletic Directors (Box 3)
  - National Football Foundation, [4 folders] (Box 4)
  - National Football Foundation Hall of Fame (Box 4)
  - Officials - Ranking Lists (Box 4)
  - Pan-African - USA Track Meet (Box 4)
  - Personnel - RESTRICTED [Personnel Information]
    - Resignations from Physical Education and Athletics (Box 4)
    - Promotions, Recommendations, Appointments (Box 4)
    - Duties, 1965-1970 (Box 4)
    - Athletic Staff Benefits (Box 4)
    - Directory, 1963-1964 (Box 4)
    - Parker, Ace - Resignation (Box 4)
  - Physical Education
    - Program, 1961-1969 (Box 4)
    - Sabbaticals (Box 4)
    - Proposed Major (Box 4)
    - Requirements, 1967 (Box 4)
    - Curricular Changes, 1968-1970 (Box 4)
    - Manual, rev. 1967 (Box 4)
    - Reports, presented by John Friedrich (Box 4)
    - Annual Reports (Men's), 1964, 1967-1969 (Box 4)
    - Pamphlets (Box 4)
    - Requirements, 1968 (Box 4)
    - Budget, 1967-1972 (Box 4)
    - Staff Meeting Minutes, 1964-1971 (Box 4)
  - Policy and Procedures (Box 4)
  - Price, James L., 1965-1966 (Box 4)
  - Public Relations (Box 4)
  - Purchasing Procedures (Box 4)
  - Pye, Kenneth (Chancellor) (Box 4)
  - Radio - Basketball and Football, 1965-1970 (Box 4)
  - Radio/TV Survey of University Athletics, 1968 (Box 4)
  - Rauch, Henry (Box 4)
  - Recommendations (Box 4)
  - Recreation and Intramurals Facilities Committee, 1965-1966 (Box 4)
  - Recruiting Infractions (Box 4)
  - Recruiting (Box 4)
  - Reising, Robert W. (Box 4)
  - Reports to the President
    - 1959-1963 (Box 4)
    - 1963-1972 (Box 4)
  - Rugby Club, 1967-1969 (Box 4)
  - Sanford, Terry (Box 4)
  - Scholarships - RESTRICTED [Student Information]
    - 1968-1971 (Box 4)
    - Hanes Lassiter (Box 4)
    - Glenn E. Mann, Jr., Memorial Fund (Box 4)
    - Cameron (Box 4)
    - Robert L. Chambers (Box 4)
    - N. E. Edgerton (Box 4)
  - Score-tron, 1964-1968 (Box 4)
  - Self-Study Report on Athletics (Box 4)
  - William Senhauser Award - Intramural, 1965 (Box 4)
  - Soccer Club - Graduate, 1967-1968 (Box 4)
  - Soccer
    - Intercollegiate Soccer Football Association (Box 4)
    - N.C. Soccer League (Box 4)
  - Speeches (Box 4)
  - Sports Hall of Fame Interview, c. 1969 (Box 4)
  - Sports Illustrated - Silver Anniversary Team, 1966 (Box 4)
  - Staff Manual, 1967-1968 (Box 4)
  - Student Athletic Fees (Box 4)
  - Student Health, 1964 (Box 4)
  - Summer Recreation Fitness Program, 1966 (Box 4)
  - Summer Session, 1967 (Box 4)
  - Television
    - Football, 1963-1965 (Box 4)
    - National and Regional, 1963-1970 (Box 4)
    - Show for Coaches (Box 4)
  - Television/Radio and Microwave Center, 1966-1969 (Box 5)
  - Together Magazine (Box 5)
  - Tuition Problems - Grant-in-Aid Costs and ACC Limits, 1965-1968 (Box 5)
  - Tickets - Changes for Season Tickets (Box 5)
  - Tennis - RESTRICTED [Personnel and Student Information]
    - Coaches (Box 5)
    - Program (Box 5)
  - Tutoring Policy, 1968 - RESTRICTED [Student Information] (Box 5)
  - U.S. Golf Association Membership (Box 5)
  - U.S. Olympic Committee, [3 folders] (Box 5)
  - Wade, Wallace - Benefit Dinner (Box 5)
  - Waters, Bucky (Box 5)
  - Werber, William (Box 5)
  - World War II Correspondence from Servicemen-Athletes (Box 5)
  - Wrestling Program (Box 5)
  - WTVD Intercollegiate Track and Field Championships, 1967 (Box 5)
  - The "X" Files [Complaints and comments about Duke athletics], [2 folders] (Box 5)
  - Yacht Racing Association, 1962-1963 (Box 5)
  - Youth Camps, Inc., 1968-1969 (Box 5)
  - Zwirko, Bob (Box 5)
- Correspondence
  - 1942 (Box 5)
  - 1943 (Box 5)
  - 1944 (Box 5)
  - 1945 (Box 5)
  - 1946 (Box 5)
  - 1947 (Box 5)
  - 1948 (Box 5)
  - 1949 (Box 5)
  - 1950 (Box 5)
  - 1951 (Box 5)
  - 1952 (Box 5)
  - 1953 (Box 5)
  - 1954 (Box 5)
  - 1955 (Box 5)
  - 1956 (Box 5)
  - 1957 (Box 5)
  - 1958 (Box 5)
  - 1959 (Box 5)
  - 1960 (Box 5)
  - 1961 (Box 5)
  - 1962 (Box 5)
  - 1963 (Box 5)
  - 1964 (Box 5)
  - 1965 (Box 5)
  - 1966 (Box 5)
  - 1967 (Box 5)
  - 1968 (Box 5)
  - 1969 (Box 5)
  - 1970 (Box 5)
  - 1971 (Box 5)
  - [no date] (Box 5)
  - Cameron Boulevard (N.C. 751), July 31, 1969-August 22, 1969 (Box 6)
  - Cameron Stadium, January 1972, [3 folders] (Box 6)
  - Ex-Players April 1972 and May 1972 (Box 6)
  - Hall of Fame
    - January 21, 1938-June 18, 1969 (Box 6)
    - June 17, 1969-June 18, 1969 (Box 6)
    - June 19, 1969-October 23, 1969 (Box 6)
    - November 5, 1969-December 2, 1969 (Box 6)
    - December 2, 1969-December 8, 1969 (Box 6)
    - December 8, 1969 (Box 6)
    - December 8, 1969-December 18, 1969 (Box 6)
  - Retirement
    - December 29, 1971-May 25, 1972 (Box 6)
    - January 1972, [5 folders] (Box 6)
    - January 1972-February 1972 (Box 6)
    - February 3, 1972-April 10, 1972 (Box 6)
    - April 1972-May 1972 (Box 6)
    - May 1972, [3 folders] (Box 6)
    - May 1972-June 1972, [2 folders] (Box 6)
    - June 1972-July 1972 (Box 6)
    - July 1972-September 1972 (Box 6)
  - 1973, [no date] (Box 6)
  - Mrs. W.P. Few, [no date] (Box 6)
- Clippings
  - [no date] (Box 6)
  - 1965-1970 (Box 6)
  - Tarheel (Box 6)
- Manuals and Printed Material
  - NCAA Official Rules (Basketball) Handbook, 1965 (Box 6)
  - NCAA Manual (Constitution and Bylaws), 1968 (Box 6)
  - Report of the 1963 NCAA Television Committee (Box 6)
  - Procedure Manual for Implementation of the 1.600 Rule [2 versions] (Box 6)
  - Recommended 1972-1973 NCAA Television Plan (Box 6)
  - NCAA National Collegiate Basketball Championship Handbook (Box 6)
  - NCAA National Collegiate Lacrosse Championship Handbook (Box 6)
  - NCAA National Collegiate Soccer Championship Handbook (Box 6)
  - NCAA Annual Reports, 1970-1971 (Box 6)
  - 64th Annual Convention Program, 1970 (Box 6)
  - ACC Constitution and Bylaws, 1953 (Box 6)
  - ACC Constitution and Bylaws, 1954 (Box 6)
- Scrapbooks
  - Scrapbook Part 1, 1929-1972 (Box 7)
  - Scrapbook Part 2, 1929-1972 (Box 8)
  - Scrapbook Part 3: Poster, 1929-1972 (Oversize-folder 1)
  - Rose Bowl Part 1, 1939-1942 (Box 9)
  - Rose Bowl Part 2, 1939-1942 (Box 10)
  - Sugar Bowl, 1945 (Box 12)
  - Sugar Bowl: Loose photographs, 1945 (Box 11)